<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>LDaCA Resources on LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/</link><description>Recent content in LDaCA Resources on LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 14:51:49 +1100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>LDaCA Software Tools</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/ldaca-software-tools/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 14:51:49 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/ldaca-software-tools/</guid><description>A variety of LDaCA open-source tools are available at our GitHub organisation. Highlights include:
Metadata Editor Crate-O: A tool that allows you to create and update Research Object Crates (RO-Crates) using a web interface, and with metadata spreadsheets. It provides researchers with a relatively simple way to describe their data using the best practices in formal metadata description.
Data Storage OCFL-js, a library that implements the Oxford Common File Layout (OCFL): A specification for laying out digital collections on file or object storage.</description></item><item><title>Licenses</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/licenses/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 12:05:32 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/licenses/</guid><description>Specifies the license(s) that data contributors have applied to the content of their collection, including the content coverage of that license.
A Corpus of Oz Early English (COOEE) All content: Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)
AustLit All content: Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)
Australian Radio Talkback All content: Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)
Braided Channels All content: Attribution-NoDerivatives 3.0 Australia (CC BY-ND 3.0 AU)
International Corpus of English (Aus) All content: Attribution 4.</description></item><item><title>Metadata</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/metadata/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:49:31 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/metadata/</guid><description>Metadata is often defined as &amp;lsquo;data about data&amp;rsquo;. High-quality metadata is important in making data FAIR:
Findable: Metadata is the starting point for searching data collections. For example, if we want to find data in a particular language, this will only be possible for data that has a language recorded in its metadata. (Tracking languages is in itself problematic, see below.) Accessible: Access conditions that apply to data should be part of the associated metadata.</description></item><item><title>Guidance for Data Governance Decisions</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/guidance-for-data-governance-decisions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 12:09:10 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/guidance-for-data-governance-decisions/</guid><description>Purpose 1. Access Conditions 1.1 Legal, moral, and ethical constraints 1.2 Licensing 2. Persistent Identifiers 3. Metadata 4. Appendix: Determining Copyright Purpose Data governance defines policies, roles, responsibilities and procedures for ongoing use and storage of data, as well as for access to data. Effective data governance maximises sustainability, while ensuring data integrity and protecting research participants. Long-term sustainability requires a data management plan.
This document provides guidance on some components of data governance that are key to a data management plan, including access conditions, licensing, persistent identifiers, and metadata.</description></item><item><title>Data Onboarding Process</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/data-onboarding-process/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 13:59:34 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/data-onboarding-process/</guid><description>Purpose Onboarding Process 1. Initiating contact between LDaCA and Data Stewards 2. Work Plan 3. Determining appropriate governance and access conditions 4. Preparing data for cataloguing in LDaCA 5. Ongoing engagement Purpose This document outlines the standards and processes that support the onboarding of language collections to LDaCA. A successful onboarding will result in the collection being catalogued with LDaCA and made available in accordance with the specified access conditions.</description></item><item><title>Access Policy</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/access-policy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 12:49:58 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/access-policy/</guid><description>Purpose 1. Access Types and Licensing Classification of Access Types 2. Onboarding Data to LDaCA LDaCA Responsibilities Data Steward Responsibilities 3. Ongoing Data Management Strategy 4. Supporting Information LDaCA Terms of Use Privacy Policy Takedown Policy Purpose This document outlines the LDaCA Access Policy, which is developed to accommodate the goal of making data appropriately accessible, in accordance with legal, moral and ethical considerations of data sharing, and tailored to meet the needs and requirements of different data collections.</description></item><item><title>Determining Access Conditions</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/determining-access-conditions/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 12:07:19 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/determining-access-conditions/</guid><description>Step 1: Consider access condition(s) for the entire collection Step 2: Organise relevant materials Step 3: Define the license terms Step 4: Determine authorisation level Options for access by application LDaCA recommends the following workflow to determine the access conditions to be outlined in the license. Examples of existing data access licenses can be found here.
Step 1: Consider access condition(s) for the entire collection Do the same access conditions apply to the entire collection?</description></item><item><title>Obtaining a DOI</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/obtaining-a-doi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 15:42:57 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/ldaca-resources/obtaining-a-doi/</guid><description>How do I get a DOI for my dataset? Through the collection’s custodial organisation:
Identify the collection’s custodial organisation – a university or research organisation that funded, sponsored, published, approved, or has a current or historical stakeholder interest in the research project that collected the data.
In many cases, contacting the university library about getting a DOI for a dataset is a good starting point. Alternatively, an enquiry may be made with the research repository of the custodial organisation regarding options for getting a DOI.</description></item></channel></rss>