<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>LDaCA - Language Data Commons of Australia</title><link>https://language-research-technology.github.io/LDaCA-website/</link><description>Introducing the Language Data Commons of Australia.</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>info @ ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Comons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info @ ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Comons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 15:28:35 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://language-research-technology.github.io/LDaCA-website/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dummy Blog Post</title><link>https://language-research-technology.github.io/LDaCA-website/moreblog/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 15:28:35 +1000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://language-research-technology.github.io/LDaCA-website/moreblog/</guid><description>Written by Simon Musgrave
Data is becoming increasingly important in today’s world, so corpus linguists might feel that the rest of the world is finally catching up. But the rest of the world are bringing with them new approaches to how data is handled. This means that fields such as corpus linguistics may need to reassess their practices. Such reassessment includes addressing concerns about how data is stored and who can access it (data stewardship) – concerns that area part of the Open Science movement, ultimately grounded on principles of equity and accountability.</description></item><item><title>What are the FAIR and CARE principles and why should corpus linguists know about them?</title><link>https://language-research-technology.github.io/LDaCA-website/fair-and-care/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 15:28:35 +1000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://language-research-technology.github.io/LDaCA-website/fair-and-care/</guid><description>Written by Simon Musgrave
Data is becoming increasingly important in today’s world, so corpus linguists might feel that the rest of the world is finally catching up. But the rest of the world are bringing with them new approaches to how data is handled. This means that fields such as corpus linguistics may need to reassess their practices. Such reassessment includes addressing concerns about how data is stored and who can access it (data stewardship) – concerns that are a part of the Open Science movement, ultimately grounded on principles of equity and accountability.</description></item></channel></rss>