<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Crate-O on LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/</link><description>Recent content in Crate-O on LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:01:02 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Create an RO-Crate</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/create-ro-crate/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 16:01:02 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/create-ro-crate/</guid><description>This guide takes you through the steps to create an RO-Crate metadata file, using a top-level collection for language data as an example.
Open Directory Open Crate-O in a compatible browser. In the Main Menu, select Open Directory. Navigate to a folder where the RO-Crate will be saved, or create a new one, then confirm your selection. For the pop-up message asking Let site view files?, select View Files. Your current working directory will be displayed in the Selected Directory section in the Mode Selector.</description></item><item><title>General</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/general/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 15:43:09 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/general/</guid><description>Crate-O Crate-O is a browser-based editor that allows you to create and update Research Object Crates (RO-Crates), either using the web interface or with metadata from a spreadsheet. It provides researchers with a relatively simple way to describe their data using best practice in formal metadata description.
RO-Crate is a way of packaging research data that stores the data together with its associated metadata and other component files, such as the data license.</description></item><item><title>Basic Navigation</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/basic-navigation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 15:42:05 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/user-guides/crate-o/basic-navigation/</guid><description>Jump to: Main Menu Mode Selector Current Entity Property Groups Entity Properties Entity Navigator Main Menu Crate-O Main Menu Image Source: LDaCA From the main menu, the following options are available:
File Option Description Open Directory Select a directory/folder to locate or set where files are saved. Load Files Load files from the selected directory into this RO-Crate. Bulk Add Select a spreadsheet from a different directory to assist you with metadata description.</description></item></channel></rss>