<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>About on LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/</link><description>Recent content in About on LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 11:20:35 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Principles</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/principles/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/principles/</guid><description>The Language Data Commons of Australia aims to ensure long-term access to language data collections for analysis and reuse. Sustainable management of and access to these significant collections of intangible cultural heritage are underpinned by two sets of complementary guiding principles of data management and stewardship, namely the FAIR and CARE principles.
FAIR Principles The FAIR principles were first published by a group of stakeholders representing academia, industry, funding agencies, and scholarly publishers.</description></item><item><title>Frequently Asked Questions</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/faqs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/faqs/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Collections</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/sample-collections/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/sample-collections/</guid><description>LDaCA has begun adding data sets, including:
Corpus of Oz Early English COOEE: a collection of texts written in Australia between 1788 and 1900. The corpus is divided into four time periods (1788–1825, 1826–1850, 1851–1875 and 1876–1900) each holding about 500,000 words. Four registers were defined for CoOEE: the Speech-based Register (SB), the Private Written Register (PrW), the Public Written Register (PcW) and the register of Government English (GE). In every Period 1-4 there is a similar number of words in the different registers.</description></item><item><title>Organisation</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/organisation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/organisation/</guid><description>LDaCA is one strand of the partnership between the Australian Research Data Commons (ARDC) and the School of Languages and Cultures at the University of Queensland. This partnership includes a number of projects that explore language-related technologies, data collection infrastructure and Indigenous capability programs. These projects are being led out of the Language Technology and Data Analytics Lab (LADAL), which is overseen by Professor Michael Haugh and Dr Martin Schweinberger.</description></item><item><title>Technologies</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/technologies/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/about/technologies/</guid><description>LDaCA is basing its data storage on Research Object Crates and the Oxford Common File Layout, which are described below. The overall approach is informed by the Arkisto platform, taking the view that research data has interest and value that extends beyond funding cycles and its long-term preservation and accessibility must continue to be managed. This presentation gives further details of the technical architecture.
Research Object Crates (RO-Crate) A Research Object (RO) is a structured archive of all the items that contributed to the research outcome, including their identifiers, provenance, relations and annotations.</description></item></channel></rss>