<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 09:45:50 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Persistent Identifiers (PIDs) and Digital Object Identifiers (DOIs)</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/persistent-identifiers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 09:45:50 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/persistent-identifiers/</guid><description>by Maria Weaver
We have learned from conversations with data stewards over the last two years that some are new to the practice of using persistent identifiers (PIDs) for data collections. This blog post will hopefully offer some guidance by briefly providing some background information and addressing the common questions we receive about PIDs and Digital Object Identifiers (DOIs).
A brief overview of persistent identifiers Most of us are familiar with the concept of identifiers (IDs); they mark and individualise a person through life, from their name at birth through to IDs assigned at school, at work and in other contexts.</description></item><item><title>Crate-O - a drop-in linked data metadata editor for RO-Crate (and other) linked data in repositories and beyond</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-crate-o/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-crate-o/</guid><description>PDF version | Powerpoint Version
Developer Track Session 2 Time: 05 June 2024, 09:00 - 10:30 · Location: Drottningporten 2
Crate-O - A drop-in linked data metadata editor for RO-Crate (and other) linked data in repositories and beyond
Peter Sefton, Alvin Sebastian, Moises Sacal Bonequi, Rosanna Smith
University of Queensland, Australia
Research Object Crate is a metadata packaging standard which has been widely adopted over the last few years in research contexts and which debuted at Open Repositories with a workshop in 2019.</description></item><item><title>Five ways RO-Crate data packages are important for repositories</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-ro-crate/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-ro-crate/</guid><description>PDF version | Powerpoint Version
Five ways RO-Crate data packages are important for repositories Presented at: The 19th International Conference on Open Repositories, June 3-6th 2024, Göteborg, Sweden
Session: Presentations: Integrations for Research Data Management
Time: 05/June/2024: 11:00 - 12:30 · Location: Drottningporten 1
Peter Sefton*, Stian Soiland-Reyes**
*University of Queensland, Australia; **The University of Manchester, UK
Research Object Crate is a linked data metadata packaging standard which has been widely adopted in research contexts.</description></item><item><title>A comprehensive, open and sustainable set of principles and tools for low (and high) resource Archival Repositories</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-pilars/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-pilars/</guid><description>PDF version | Powerpoint Version
From “R-Drive to RRKive” – a comprehensive, open and sustainable set of principles and tools for low (and high) resource archival-repositories Presented at: The 19th International Conference on Open Repositories, June 3-6th 2024, Göteborg, Sweden
Session: Presentations: Open and Sustainable Infrastructure
Time: 04/June/2024: 13:30 - 15:00 · Location: Drottningporten 1
Peter Sefton*, Robert McLellan*, Michael Lynch**, Moises Sacal Bonequi*, Nick Thieberger***
*University of Queensland; **University of Sydney; ***University of Melbourne</description></item><item><title>IDIL 2022–2032: Voices of Country Action Plan — An LDaCA Discussion Paper</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/idil/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 09:45:50 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/idil/</guid><description>by Rosanna Smith, Simon Musgrave, Robert McLellan and Ben Foley
International Decade of Indigenous Languages 2022–2032 The world&amp;rsquo;s billions of people use thousands of languages in myriads of ways, through communication by speech, sign, text and song (Evans, 2022). Diversity of language is critical for conveying the world&amp;rsquo;s knowledges and expressing the range of human experiences. Australia is in an area of great language diversity, with hundreds of languages on this continent.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Kalin Stefanov</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/kalin-stefanov/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 14:29:40 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/kalin-stefanov/</guid><description>This blog post features an interview with Kalin Stefanov (ARC DECRA Fellow at Monash University), who is working on an Australian Sign Language (Auslan) project. We would like to thank Chief Investigator Louisa Willoughby for first letting us know about Kalin’s work, and Kalin for graciously agreeing to the interview and providing his thoughts.
Kalin Stefanov, Monash University Image Source: Kalin Stefanov How did you get interested in sign language?</description></item><item><title>What happened to the Australian National Corpus (AusNC)?</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/ausnc/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 15:12:12 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/ausnc/</guid><description>by Simon Musgrave and Michael Haugh
Overview of the Australian National Corpus (AusNC) The Australian National Corpus (AusNC) project was an important precursor to the Language Data Commons of Australia (LDaCA) project. Important aims and motivations of the LDaCA project are to secure language data in Australia and to make it easily available to researchers (and other interested parties). But language researchers have been aware of these issues for some time and the AusNC was an earlier attempt to address them.</description></item><item><title>Graduate Digital Research Fellowship</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/gdrf/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 09:00:00 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/gdrf/</guid><description>In 2018, when he was working at The University of Queensland&amp;rsquo;s (UQ) Research Computing Centre (RCC), Marco Fahmi (former LDaCA Project Manager) initiated a Graduate Digital Research Fellowship (GDRF) program focused on researchers in the Humanities and Social Sciences (HASS). The program has run in some years since then, hosted by the RCC (2019) and also by the UQ Graduate School (2020).
In 2023, the program ran again, this time under the auspices of the Australian Text Analytics Program (ATAP).</description></item><item><title>Interview with our Chief Investigators - Part 2</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/interview-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 07:51:43 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/interview-2/</guid><description>The Australian Text Analytics Platform (ATAP) and the Language Data Commons of Australia (LDaCA) are collaborative projects led by the University of Queensland and supported by the Australian Research Data Commons to develop infrastructure for researchers who work with language data. In this blog post series, we feature interviews with the Chief Investigators of the two projects. In each post, we present their answers to three questions:
What is your role in these projects?</description></item><item><title>Towards a Generic Research Data Commons: A highly scalable standards-based repository framework for Language and other Humanities data</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/arkisto-stack-or-2023/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/arkisto-stack-or-2023/</guid><description>Download as PDF
This presentation was delivered by Peter Sefton at the Open Repositories 2023 conference in South Africa on 2023-06-14 in the Presentations: Discipline specific systems with FAIR principles session.
This contains the slides and complete speaker notes, which have been edited after the conference.
We will present a standards-based generalised architecture for large-scale data* repositories for research and preservation illustrated with real-world examples drawn from a number of languages and cultural archive projects.</description></item><item><title>Interview with our Chief Investigators - Part 1</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/interview-1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 15:28:35 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/interview-1/</guid><description>The Australian Text Analytics Platform (ATAP) and the Language Data Commons of Australia (LDaCA) are collaborative projects led by the University of Queensland and supported by the Australian Research Data Commons to develop infrastructure for researchers who work with language data. In this blog post series, we feature interviews with the Chief Investigators of the two projects. In each post, we present their answers to three questions:
What is your role in these projects?</description></item><item><title>Language data in Australia - Mapping a conceptual landscape</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/data-map/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 15:28:35 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/data-map/</guid><description>The data which is being made accessible through the Language Data Commons of Australia will contribute to the task of documenting language use and language behaviour in Australia. But what does this include? We are aware of many data sources and, in the short term, the important questions are about priorities:
What will be immediately useful? What data is stored precariously? What relationships can be leveraged? But in thinking for the long term, there is value in asking the question from a more conceptual point of view:</description></item><item><title>Designing a metadata ecosystem for language research based on Research Object Crate (RO-Crate)</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/ldaca-metadata-ecosystem-eresearch-2022/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/ldaca-metadata-ecosystem-eresearch-2022/</guid><description>PDF version
By Peter Sefton, Nick Thieberger, Marco La Rosa, Simon Musgrave, River Tae Smith, Moises Sacal Bonequi – delivered by Peter Sefton at eResearch 2022 in Brisbane
This work is licensed under CC BY 4.0. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
This presentation will look at how a Metadata Standard - RO-Crate - with Metadata Profile (the Language Data Commons) is being developed and implemented. Two major collections are collaborating on the standard, PARADISEC and the Language Data Commons of Australia (LDaCA).</description></item><item><title>A CARE and FAIR-ready distributed access control system for human-created data using the Australian Access Federation and beyond</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/fair-care-eresearch-2022/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/fair-care-eresearch-2022/</guid><description>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
Download as PDF
This is a write-up of a talk given at eResearch Australasia 2022, delivered by Peter Sefton, with some additional detail.
By: Peter Sefton, Jenny Fewster, Moises Sacal Bonequi, Cale Johnstone, Catherine Travis, River Tae Smith, Patrick Carnuccio
Edited by: Simon Musgrave
The Language Data Commons of Australia Data Partnerships (LDaCA) and the Australian Text Analytics Platform (ATAP) are building towards a scalable and flexible language data and analytics commons.</description></item><item><title>HASS RDC Technical Advisory Group Meeting LDaCA &amp; ATAP Intro</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/rdc-tech-meeting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 15:28:35 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/rdc-tech-meeting/</guid><description>This is a presentation Peter Sefton gave to the Humanities, Arts and Social Sciences Research Data Commons and Indigenous Research Capability Program Technical Advisory Group on Friday 11th February 2022.
Thanks to Simon Musgrave for reviewing this and adding a little detail here and there.
(This is also available on Dr Sefton&amp;rsquo;s site)
PDF version
The Language Data Commons of Australia Data Partnerships (LDaCA) and the Australian Text Analytics Platform (ATAP) are establishing a scalable and flexible language data and analytics commons.</description></item><item><title>What are the FAIR and CARE principles and why should corpus linguists know about them?</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/fair-and-care/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 15:28:35 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/fair-and-care/</guid><description>FAIR and CARE Data is becoming increasingly important in today’s world, so corpus linguists might feel that the rest of the world is finally catching up. But the rest of the world are bringing with them new approaches to how data is handled. This means that fields such as corpus linguistics may need to reassess their practices. Such reassessment includes addressing concerns about how data is stored and who can access it (data stewardship) – concerns that are a part of the Open Science movement, ultimately grounded on principles of equity and accountability.</description></item></channel></rss>