<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Case Studies on LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/</link><description>Recent content in Case Studies on LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 16:02:05 +1100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Fieldwork in Papua New Guinea</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/fieldwork-png/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:55:01 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/fieldwork-png/</guid><description>by Harriet Sheppard
My fieldwork experience, in many ways, conforms to stereotypes of language fieldwork – a community outsider working with a smaller language community located far from an urban centre. For my postgraduate research, I documented and described grammatical topics of Sudest (known as Vanga Vanatɨna by its speakers), an Oceanic language spoken in Papua New Guinea (PNG). The language is spoken on the islands of Vanatinai (also known as Sudest and Tagula) and Yeina in the Louisiade Archipelago, approximately 350 kilometres southeast of the PNG mainland.</description></item><item><title>Sydney Speaks</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/sydney-speaks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:53:30 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/sydney-speaks/</guid><description>by Catherine Travis and Cale Johnstone
Introducing the Sydney Speaks project Sydney Speaks is a large-scale sociolinguistic project, funded through the ARC Centre of Excellence for the Dynamics of Language (2014-2022), led by Catherine Travis at the ANU.
The Sydney Speaks Corpora Contemporary linguistic recordings (collected 2015-present): Sydney Speaks 2010s Legacy linguistic recordings (Collected 1977-1981): Sydney Social Dialect Survey Legacy oral histories (collected 1987-1988): NSW Bicentennial Oral History Collection Data access concerns Combining legacy and contemporary data collections References Sydney Speaks Corpus and Publications Since 2015, the Sydney Speaks project has recorded the spontaneous speech of Sydneysiders for the purpose of documenting and exploring Australian English as spoken in Australia’s largest and most ethnically and linguistically diverse city.</description></item></channel></rss>