<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Case Studies on LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/</link><description>Recent content in Case Studies on LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 16:17:33 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Master's Research Project</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/masters-research-project/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 16:17:33 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/masters-research-project/</guid><description>by Teresa Chan
During a Master of Applied Linguistics degree at UNSW Sydney, I was given the opportunity to enrol in a course in which students become interns in the School of Humanities and Languages&amp;rsquo; Language Processing Lab. Although I would still have readings and assessments to complete, the teaching model would be different to a standard postgraduate course: I would attend regular online lab meetings with my supervisor and other interns, and design and conduct my own research project.</description></item><item><title>Data Management in Language Technology: A Case Study of Appen</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/data-mangement-appen/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 15:12:12 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/data-mangement-appen/</guid><description>by Rosanna Smith
Founded in Sydney in 1996, Appen is a technology company that collects and improves data for the purposes of training and developing machine learning and artificial intelligence systems. During my time at Appen, a significant part of my work involved a diverse range of projects for both automatic speech recognition (ASR) and text-to-speech (TTS) technologies, including phonetic transcription, grapheme-to-phoneme or letter-to-sound (L2S) rule development, and part-of-speech (POS) annotation.</description></item><item><title>Fieldwork in Papua New Guinea</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/fieldwork-png/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:55:01 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/fieldwork-png/</guid><description>by Harriet Sheppard
&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; HEAD Harriet on an outrigger boat off Vanatɨna Harriet Sheppard ======= Harriet on an outrigger boat off Vanatɨna Image Source: Harriet Sheppard >>>>>>> 9f58ceb079af18ba120416f7c08072972bfcd590 My fieldwork experience, in many ways, conforms to stereotypes of language fieldwork – a community outsider working with a smaller language community located far from an urban centre. For my postgraduate research, I documented and described grammatical topics of Sudest (known as Vanga Vanatɨna by its speakers), an Oceanic language spoken in Papua New Guinea (PNG).</description></item><item><title>Sydney Speaks</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/sydney-speaks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:53:30 +1100</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/resources/general-resources/case-studies/sydney-speaks/</guid><description>by Catherine Travis and Cale Johnstone
Introducing the Sydney Speaks project Sydney Speaks is a large-scale sociolinguistic project, funded through the ARC Centre of Excellence for the Dynamics of Language (2014-2022), led by Catherine Travis at the ANU.
The Sydney Speaks Corpora Contemporary linguistic recordings (collected 2015-present): Sydney Speaks 2010s Legacy linguistic recordings (Collected 1977-1981): Sydney Social Dialect Survey Legacy oral histories (collected 1987-1988): NSW Bicentennial Oral History Collection Data access concerns Combining legacy and contemporary data collections References Sydney Speaks Corpus and Publications Since 2015, the Sydney Speaks project has recorded the spontaneous speech of Sydneysiders for the purpose of documenting and exploring Australian English as spoken in Australia’s largest and most ethnically and linguistically diverse city.</description></item></channel></rss>