<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>General Resources on LDaCA</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/</link>
    <description>Recent content in General Resources on LDaCA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 16:54:49 +1100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 14:19:16 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/publications/</guid>
      <description>The Open Handbook of Linguistic Data Management Edited by Andrea L. Berez-Kroeker, Bradley McDonnell, Eve Koller, Lauren B. Collister. MIT Press 2022.
&amp;ldquo;A guide to principles and methods for the management, archiving, sharing, and citing of linguistic research data, especially digital data. “Doing language science” depends on collecting, transcribing, annotating, analyzing, storing, and sharing linguistic research data. This volume offers a guide to linguistic data management, engaging with current trends toward the transformation of linguistics into a more data-driven and reproducible scientific endeavor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organisations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/organisations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 14:18:49 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/organisations/</guid>
      <description>Australian Organisations Australian Linguistic Society (ALS) The national organisation for linguists and linguistics in Australia. Its primary goal is to further interest in and support for linguistics research and teaching in Australia.
Applied Linguistics Association of Australia (ALAA) The national professional organisation for applied linguistics in Australia. It welcomes academics, teachers, researchers, students and members of the wider community to join and become part of an active community interested in questions, issues and problems that can be understood and addressed through a focus on language in our world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Language Archives</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/language-archives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 14:18:36 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/language-archives/</guid>
      <description>Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC) Holds 14,500 hours of audio recordings and 2,000 hours of video recordings that might otherwise have been lost. These recordings are of performance, narrative, singing, and other oral tradition. This amounts to 150 terabytes and represents 1,315 languages, mainly from the Pacific region.
Living Archive of Aboriginal Languages (LAAL) A digital archive of endangered literature in Australian Indigenous languages of the Northern Territory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 14:18:11 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/ethics/</guid>
      <description>Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies Code of Ethics
Australian Linguistic Society policies
Includes Policy on Linguistic rights of Aboriginal and Islander communities and Statement of Ethics.
Australian Code for the Responsible Conduct of Research, 2018
Linguistic Society of America:
Ethics Statement 2019 Further resources Tromsø recommendations for citation of research data in linguistics
Language and linguistics datasets are often not cited, or cited imprecisely, because of confusion surrounding the proper methods for citing them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Language Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/language-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 14:18:01 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/language-projects/</guid>
      <description>Indigenous Languages of Australia 50 Words Project Showcases words from 64 languages across Australia, with further languages being added regularly as more communities around Australia become involved. For each language, you can hear the words spoken via a map that shows the general location of the language.
AustLang Provides a controlled vocabulary of persistent identifiers, a thesaurus of languages and peoples, and information about Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander languages which has been assembled from referenced sources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indigenous Knowledge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/indigenous-knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 14:17:24 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/indigenous-knowledge/</guid>
      <description>Protocols for using First Nations Cultural and Intellectual Property in the Arts (Australia Council). Citing Indigenous elders and knowledge keepers: Templates For Citing Indigenous Elders and Knowledge Keepers (Lorisia MacLeod) University of Alberta Library&amp;rsquo;s guide University of Alberta Library&amp;rsquo;s blog TK Labels: Traditional Knowledge labels are an initiative for Indigenous communities and local organizations. Developed through sustained partnership and testing within Indigenous communities across multiple countries, the Labels allow communities to express local and specific conditions for sharing and engaging in future research and relationships in ways that are consistent with already existing community rules, governance and protocols for using, sharing and circulating knowledge and data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Useful Tools</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/useful-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 16:27:35 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/useful-tools/</guid>
      <description>Audacity A free, easy-to-use, multi-track audio editor and recorder for Windows, macOS, GNU/Linux and other operating systems.
ELAN A tool for making time-aligned annotations on audio and video recordings.
Praat Free software for doing phonetics by computer.
FieldWorks Software tools for managing linguistic and cultural data. FieldWorks supports tasks ranging from the initial entry of collected data through to the preparation of data for publication, including dictionary development, interlinearization of texts, morphological analysis, and other publications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glossary</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/glossary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 12:07:09 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/resources/general-resources/glossary/</guid>
      <description>Access ConditionsConditions which specify who can access data and what they can do with that data. A well-governed archival repository has mechanisms in place to administer and implement such conditions which will be specified on a data license.ADAAustralian Data Archive. A national service for the collection and preservation of digital research data.
More informationADM&amp;#43;SARC Centre of Excellence for Automated Decision-Making and Society. It brings together universities, industry, government and the community to support the development of responsible, ethical and inclusive automated decision-making.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
