<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>RO-Crate - Tag - LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/tags/ro-crate/</link><description>RO-Crate - Tag - LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/tags/ro-crate/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Crate-O - a drop-in linked data metadata editor for RO-Crate (and other) linked data in repositories and beyond</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-crate-o/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Sefton</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-crate-o/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="2024-OR-Crate-O.pdf">PDF version</a> | <a href="2024-OR-Crate-O.pptx">Powerpoint Version</a></p>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<h1 id="developer-track-session-2">Developer Track Session 2</h1>
<p>Time: 05 June 2024, 09:00 - 10:30 · Location: Drottningporten 2</p>
<p>Crate-O - A drop-in linked data metadata editor for RO-Crate (and other) linked data in repositories and beyond</p>
<p>Peter Sefton, Alvin Sebastian, Moises Sacal Bonequi, Rosanna Smith</p>
<p>University of Queensland, Australia</p>
<p>Research Object Crate is a metadata packaging standard which has been widely adopted over the last few years in research contexts and which debuted at Open Repositories with a workshop in 2019.</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>Crate-O is an editor for the RO-Crate Metadata Specification.</p>
<p>RO-Crate has been presented here at Open Repositories for the last few years, and is now starting to be incorporated into many research repository solutions (though they are not always called repositories).</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>I am presenting in the next session on why RO-Crate is important for repositories.</p>
<h1 id="five-ways-ro-crate-data-packages-are-important-for-repositories">Five ways RO-Crate data packages are important for repositories</h1>
<p>Time: 05 June 2024, 11:00 - 12:30 · Location: Drottningporten 1</p>
<p>Peter Sefton*, Stian Soiland-Reyes**</p>
<p>*University of Queensland, Australia; **The University of Manchester, UK</p>
<p>Research Object Crate is a linked data metadata packaging standard which has been widely adopted in research contexts. In this presentation, we will briefly explain what RO-Crate is, how it is being adopted worldwide, then go on to list ways that RO-Crate is growing in importance in the repository world:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Uploading of complex multi-file objects means RO-Crate is compatible with any general-purpose repository that can accept a zip file (with some coding, repository services can do more with RO-Crates)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Download for well-described data objects complete with metadata from a repository rather than just a zip or file with no metadata</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Using RO-Crate metadata reduces the amount of customisation that is required in repository software, as ALL the metadata is described using the same simple, self-documenting linked-data structures, so generic display templates</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sufficiently well-described RO-Crates can be used to make data FAIR compliant, aiding in Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability and Reusability thanks to standardised metadata and mature tooling</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>And if you’re looking for a sustainable repository solution, there are tools which can run a repository from a set of static files on a storage service, in line with the ideas put forward by Suleman in the closing keynote for OR2023.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The Language Data Commons of Australia Data Partnerships (LDaCA-DP), Language Data Commons of Australia Research Data Commons (LDaCA-RDC), and Australian Text Analytics Platform (ATAP) projects received investment (<a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/DP768" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://doi.org/10.47486/DP768</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/HIR001" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://doi.org/10.47486/HIR001</a>, &amp; <a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/PL074" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://doi.org/10.47486/PL074</a>)
from the Australian Research Data Commons (ARDC).</p>
<p>The ARDC is funded by the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS).</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>A version of the Crate-O component is available as a playground for Chrome browsers only. This allows you to describe your local folders in your computer and generate an RO-Crate.</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p><a href="https://github.com/Language-Research-Technology/ro-crate-modes/blob/main/docs/soss-profiles.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://github.com/Language-Research-Technology/ro-crate-modes/blob/main/docs/soss-profiles.md</a></p>
<p>A Schema.org style Schema (SOSS) specifies a metadata vocabulary of Classes and Properties, based on the RO-Crate specification&rsquo;s use of Schema.org classes.
An RO-Crate Profile has (at least) a document that explains how metadata entities from the Schema are used for a particular purpose.
An RO-Crate Mode is a set of lightweight syntactic rules for combining SOSS Classes, Properties and DefinedTerms, expressed in a JSON file.</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>Crate-O RO-Crate Editor Mode Files are editor configurations that implement RO-Crate Metadata Profiles.</p>
<p>The configuration files are intended to form the basis of an approach for describing RO-Crate editor behaviour and can be used for RO-Crate validation.</p>
<p>Initial versions of this work were based on the Describo Profiles (which vary between versions of Describo) used to configure the Describo family of RO-Crate editing tools, currently maintained by Marco La Rosa.</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>Crate-O is a single-page front-end web app developed using the Vue Javascript framework. Vue app is built by composing and nesting modular structures called components.</p>
<p>The main part Crate-O is then bundled in the CrateEditor component (highlighted in red) that allows a user to view, add, edit and delete properties of an entity, add and delete entities, and navigate and browse all entities in the crate.</p>
<p>The CrateEditor component is exported as EMAScript Module and can be imported into any Vue web app by adding Crate-O as dependency.</p>
<p>The default main app (for showcasing) only runs in Chrome-based browsers because it requires the <code>showDirectoryPicker</code> method from File System API to access (read/write) a directory on a local machine. The feature is still experimental and only available in Chrome-based browsers. However, the CrateEditor component itself does not require that feature.</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>This slide illustrates the very basic example of embedding Crate-O CrateEditor in any Vue app.</p>
<p>The example shows a Vue Single-File Component (SFC) (*.vue)</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Inside the &lt; import the CrateEditor component from the Crate-O package</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Initialise all required variables</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Add the &lt;crate-editor&gt; tag inside the &lt;template&gt; and pass in the data via the attributes:</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>crate: a plain js object in json-ld format, usually is the result of JSON.parse() of the string content of ro-crate-metadata.json file</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>mode: a plain js object conforming to the ro-crate-mode syntax</p>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>Data can be imported into Crate-O using spreadsheets - this is an efficient way to create metadata for collections of objects. Spreadsheet skills are common and many projects have already been described using spreadsheets to describe and manage files, we work with data custodians to standardize their approach to this so that they can create rich linked-data metadata.</p>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>Crate-O can be found here <a href="https://github.com/Language-Research-Technology/crate-o" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://github.com/Language-Research-Technology/crate-o</a></p>
</section>
]]></description></item><item><title>Five ways RO-Crate data packages are important for repositories</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-ro-crate/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Sefton</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/news/posts/open-repositories-2024-ro-crate/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="2024-OR-RO-Crate.pdf">PDF version</a> | <a href="2024-OR-RO-Crate.pptx">Powerpoint Version</a></p>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<h1 id="five-ways-ro-crate-data-packages-are-important-for-repositories">Five ways RO-Crate data packages are important for repositories</h1>
<p>Presented at: The 19th International Conference on Open Repositories, June 3-6th 2024, Göteborg, Sweden</p>
<p>Session: Presentations: Integrations for Research Data Management</p>
<p>Time: 05/June/2024: 11:00 - 12:30 · Location: Drottningporten 1</p>
<p>Peter Sefton*, Stian Soiland-Reyes**</p>
<p>*University of Queensland, Australia; **The University of Manchester, UK</p>
<p>Research Object Crate is a linked data metadata packaging standard which has been widely adopted in research contexts. In this presentation, we will briefly explain what RO-Crate is, how it is being adopted worldwide, then go on to list ways that RO-Crate is growing in importance in the repository world:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Uploading of complex multi-file objects means RO-Crate is compatible with any general-purpose repository that can accept a ZIP file (with some coding, repository services can do more with RO-Crates).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Download for well-described data objects complete with metadata from a repository rather than just a ZIP or file with no metadata.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Using RO-Crate metadata reduces the amount of customisation that is required in repository software, as ALL the metadata is described using the same simple, self-documenting linked-data structures, so generic display templates.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sufficiently well-described RO-Crates can be used to make data FAIR compliant, aiding in Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability and Reusability thanks to standardised metadata and mature tooling.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>And if you’re looking for a sustainable repository solution, there are tools which can run a repository from a set of static files on a storage service, in line with the ideas put forward by Suleman in the closing keynote for OR2023.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<h2 id="uploading-of-complex-multi-file-objects">Uploading of complex multi-file objects</h2>
<p>RO-Crate [1], [2] is a data packaging format and can be used to put multiple data files together with their metadata into a package such as a ZIP, tar or disk image file. This means that as long as your repository can handle a ZIP file it can take RO-Crates.</p>
<p>RO-Crates enable data to travel with metadata.</p>
<p>Beyond simply allowing the upload of opaque RO-Crates, there are opportunities for repository software to recognise metadata in an uploaded package and to pre-populate built-in metadata forms and/or datastores. This is not a pattern the authors have seen widely implemented in comprehensive institutionally focussed repositories, although at the time of writing it is being explored in Dataverse and InvenioRDM/Zenodo. We would encourage repository developers to explore this further, particularly those working with research data. RO-Crate support is increasing in research-domain repositories; e.g. RO-Crate upload with metadata extract is supported by WorkflowHub and ROHub).</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>One of the design features of an RO-Crate is that as it can be “just a ZIP file” it can be used with any old repository that can handle ZIP files. The JSON file can also be uploaded separately. As RO-Crate adoption increases, the repository may be able to start to use the RO-Crate metadata it already has. You can/will have heard from Dieuwertje Bloemen here at OR2024 that DataVerse has support for RO-Crate metadata preview and building import/export mechanisms.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The RO-Crate specification described a method of packaging data in a folder, which can be zipped, with any kind of file.</p>
<p>This slide shows a folder of data, including a file with a typical obscure file name based on a timestamp (in this case created by a Dropbox upload from a digital camera). The RO-Crate Metadata file, in JSON Linked Data Format, can describe files. This one has a name (i.e. a title) for the file; “Cute puppy”.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>A human-readable description and preview (ro-crate-preview.html) can be in an HTML file that lives alongside the metadata. This slide shows an HTML view of the data that shows the image with its metadata, including the Schema.org <code>name</code> (equivalent to a Dublin Core <code>title</code>) for the file.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>Increasingly, research repository infrastructure is accepting RO-Crate input - this screenshot from WorkflowHub [documents the upload API[(https://about.workflowhub.eu/developer/ro-crate-api/) for submitting RO-Crate packaged descriptions of scientific workflows to the system. These can then be downloaded by others for reuse. Here, RO-Crate allows bypassing of the traditional “title, author, license, description” fields (rendered from the crate), as well as permitting user extensions on metadata to be kept in the repository.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<h2 id="ro-crate-is-a-packaging-format-suitable-for-downloads">RO-Crate is a packaging format suitable for downloads</h2>
<p>One of the perennial problems with downloads is that once a user has the data, it often does not come with metadata as shown on the landing page, or if present it is in an ad hoc or specialised format. RO-Crate solves this by specifying an extensible way to put linked-data metadata with data assets and to provide an HTML page or small website with the data to explain it. Thus data travels <em>with</em> its metadata and can be made human-readable.</p>
<p>RO-Crate download is already available in many data repositories. Examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;source=web&amp;rct=j&amp;opi=89978449&amp;url=https://workflowhub.eu/&amp;ved=2ahUKEwi_wuuK9qmGAxWkAHkGHb9hDngQFnoECBgQAQ&amp;usg=AOvVaw0Mgw-ytkMOTMLIPdH1AorW" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">WorkflowHub</a>: A registry for describing, sharing and publishing scientific computational workflows.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.rohub.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">ROHub</a>: A  repository of Earth Science datasets and computational methods.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://tlcmap.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">TLCMap</a>: The Time Layered Cultural map is a set of tools that work together for mapping Australian history and culture.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <a href="https://data.ldaca.org.au" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Language Data Commons of Australia data portal</a>: entirely built on RO-Crates, the underlying data consists of crates-on-disk and the API is based on RO-Crate metadata.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://wildlive.senckenberg.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Senckenberg Wildlive portal</a>: exposes metadata about automatic photo captures of endangered animals using RO-Crate.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Dataverse: at the time of writing, RO-Crate downloads are in development.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>We will encourage developers from other repository platforms to follow the Dataverse project’s lead and add RO-Crate support.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>This is a screenshot of the <a href="https://uqz.zoom.us/j/85861337752" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Gazetteer of Historical Australian Places</a> – not exactly a repository but an example of a place where people can download datasets.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>This kind of download could be added to any repository system where there is at least one file that has metadata; offer a download ZIP option that has machine-readable JSON metadata (linked data in JSON-LD) and a human-readable summary of the metadata – this one has descriptions of a few files in it.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>Every repository implementer should add FAIR Signposting – just a couple of HTTP headers – this means machines can go from an HTML landing page to the actual download without guesswork – or even better – to an RO-Crate! I’m sure you’ll hear this mentioned in one of the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;presentations=show&amp;search=herbert" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">talks</a> by Herbert van de Sompel and colleagues, such as the one on <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=475#paperID246" title="FAIRiCat: Supporting Discovery of a Repository&#39;s Interoperability Affordances" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">FAIRiCat</a>. Again, DataVerse is ahead of the curve and has already implemented this.</p>
<p>As we mentioned above, data should travel with the metadata – one example of this from the WorkflowHub is how other services like the LifeMonitor retrieves the RO-Crate and then looks for custom annotations in the metadata to pick up and connect to the testing infrastructure.  This was only possible because RO-Crate is extensible - you are not trapped with whatever 25 properties we’ve selected. The vessel is still RO-Crate, the repository didn&rsquo;t need to add anything to support the LifeMonitor.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>One of the key benefits of linked-data metadata over previous ‘legacy’ approaches, is that multiple vocabularies can be combined into a single metadata document in a way that is not possible with, say MARC, or MODS XML, and that all these vocabularies can use the same syntax and approach to describing data. This means that a simple generic RO-Crate viewer can be used to visualise any metadata whether it is basic “Who, What, Where” metadata (like Dublin Core) or domain-specific metadata like the RO-Crate metadata profile (<a href="https://w3id.org/ldac/profile" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://w3id.org/ldac/profile</a>) used by the Language Data Commons of Australia. This can be displayed alongside the core RO-Crate metadata without any expensive configuration or coding. If the recommendations are followed, the RO-Crate metadata terms are self-documenting, e.g. all the Language Data Commons terms which use a Schema.org Style approach, are defined here: <a href="https://w3id.org/ldac/terms" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://w3id.org/ldac/terms</a>.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>This slide is a repeat of one we used last year – this screenshot is a bit of (undated) DSpace documentation found following a tip from Kim Sheppard – we have included it here to illustrate that storing additional metadata (in this case METS) for an object was done by convention – it had to be stored in a special file called METS.xml. Using a linked-data system means that we no longer have to do this kind of thing – there’s still one magic file name in RO-Crate but it’s only one for the metadata and one for the HTML preview – everything else is labelled and extensible.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>This is an example of a data object in RO-Hub, which has a variety of files described in the object.</p>
<p>This site does not need to have multiple plugins for different kinds of data, as linked data has a generic structure. We saw another example of how the generic structure can be rendered in the opening example with a picture of Sefton&rsquo;s dog.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>So now we can tell all these research software developers, I know you like making new file formats, and I would love to support that in my repository, so could you perhaps use RO-Crate as the basis for making that format? Then we can pull out all the boring stuff, even for new file extensions, we just detect it’s a ZIP file and look for that magic file. If it says it’s an RO-Crate we’ll believe you.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The availability of RO-Crate editing tools opens the way for repository software to focus on access and discoverability.
We argue that the core functionality of a repository is keeping data safe and making it available with appropriate access controls (remember, not all data can be made Open Access - the A for accessibility in FAIR is about giving the right people (or other agents) access to the right data). RO-Crates require clear licensing statements to travel with data, and we will demonstrate how these have been integrated into access-control systems.</p>
<p>There is an opportunity, if RO-Crate is adopted as an interchange format, for the metadata editing functions (and authorisation) functions of a repository to be decoupled from it so the editor components for a particular metadata profile can be shared between repository instances, or handled in a more distributed architecture than in typical current repositories.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The <a href="https://describo.github.io/describo-users.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Describo</a> website mentions this integration with the Dataverse repository where the Describo RO-Crate editor can be used to enter metadata. The pattern is potentially very powerful - separate the creation of metadata from the repository so that repositories can focus on data retention and multiple other applications can be built for use by researchers or other users – closer to or embedded in systems they are already using.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The Language Data Commons of Australia team has produced an alternative to Describo known as Crate-O – this is available as a web component ready to drop in to any web app or can function stand-alone  – we use it as part of the workflow in maintaining the <a href="https://data.ldaca.edu.au/collection?id=arcp%3A%2F%2Fname%2Cdoi10.26180%252F23961609&amp;_crateId=arcp%3A%2F%2Fname%2Cdoi10.26180%252F23961609" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">data portal for the Language Data Commons of Australia</a>.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>This slide shows the beginning of an access-control process. The data was prepared in RO-Crate format using batch-processing scripts and has a license attached. The repository portal is shown here - with an indication that the user needs to log in to access the data.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The user logs in using CILogon (or another federated authentication service).</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The user is then directed to an instance of REMS - the <a href="https://github.com/CSCfi/rems/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Resource Entitlement Management System</a> (REMS) to request that a licence be granted to access the data. REMS is open-source software.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>After an approval process which may be automated, or may involve humans checking credentials, the user is directed back to the repository.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>With a repository to keep data safe and serve it using persistent identifiers, RO-Crates help make data FAIR.</p>
<p>RO-Crate is increasingly being used to describe the provenance [3] of derived data in such a way that the workflows/computation that produced it can be re-run automatically to validate it, or as a basis for new research. This might be a button on a repository to run a bioinformatics workflow, or re-run a Jupyter notebook that produces a set of plots.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>RO-Crate helps to enable FAIR research practice; RO-Crates can describe inputs, outputs and code in any combination to record research processes, and can be used to provision services.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>This slide is a collage from a <a href="https://conference.eresearch.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/1045-Alex-Ip.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">presentation at eResearch Australasia</a>, lead author Alex Ip put together showing some examples of code notebooks for text analytics and geophysics. Alex is working with the Language Data Commons of Australia team to make RO-Crate Profiles that can describe code, not just in terms of its authorship, language and inputs and outputs, but the (usually virtual) execution environment and hardware requirements needed to run it. This is a key step forward in the Interoperability and Reuse of data called for by the FAIR principles.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>There are tools which can run a repository from a set of static files on a storage service, in line with the ideas put forward by prof Suleman at OR 2023.
The team at the Language Data Commons of Australia, with partner institutions and colleagues, has been working to produce a set of tools for building Archival Repository software stacks that is based on a principled approach to keeping data safe, based on the principles presented in the Arkisto website[4] and more recently at <a href="https://w3id.org/ldac/pilars" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://w3id.org/ldac/pilars</a> the core idea is that a collection of RO-Crates in a storage service can be the basis of a repository – either using a simple on-disk directory layout or something more complicated such as an Oxford Common File Layout (OCFL) specification.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The [UTS Research Data Portal] is an example of a very minimal data repository system which uses a standard RO-Crate viewer to show RO-Crates that are sitting on file storage. This example is of an <a href="https://data.research.uts.edu.au/#view/0bacede4bd5a39993ec5088e6247cac8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">engineering dataset</a>.</p>
<br>
</section>
<section  typeof='http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/Slide' class="or_section">

<p>The Language Data Commons of Australia Data Partnerships (LDaCA-DP), Language Data Commons of Australia Research Data Commons (LDaCA-RDC), and Australian Text Analytics Platform (ATAP) projects received investment (<a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/DP768" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://doi.org/10.47486/DP768</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/HIR001" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://doi.org/10.47486/HIR001</a>, &amp; <a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/PL074" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">https://doi.org/10.47486/PL074</a>) from the Australian Research Data Commons (ARDC).</p>
<p>The ARDC is funded by the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS).</p>
</section>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>