<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>LDaCA</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/events/</link><description>Recent content on LDaCA</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ldaca.edu.au/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Events</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/events/events/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/events/events/</guid><description>Forthcoming workshops Previous workshops Webinars Office Hours
Forthcoming workshops HASS and Indigenous Research Data Commons Computational Skills Summer School 2024 The 2024 HASS and Indigenous RDC Computational Skills Summer School aims to empower participants with practical knowledge, build digital skills, and help inspire new research outcomes within these research communities.
Participation is aimed at researchers in the humanities, arts, social sciences and Indigenous fields of study. Themed streams will explore geosocial and geospatial data applications in humanities, arts, social sciences, and Indigenous research, using ARDC tools and services.</description></item><item><title>Previous Workshops</title><link>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/events/previous/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@ldaca.edu.au (Language Data Commons of Australia)</author><guid>https://www.ldaca.edu.au/events/previous/</guid><description>If your university or organisation would like to host a workshop, please contact us.
Workshop on community language corpora in Australia Australia is a highly multilingual and multicultural society, with more than 490 languages coming from around 300 ancestries and cultural traditions (ABS, 2021, 2022). For decades, the language and cultural maintenance of various immigrant groups have been under investigation by many scholars, not only in linguistics but also in history, sociology, anthropology, and other disciplines.</description></item></channel></rss>